Finding Aid for the Albert Boni Collection of Material about Photography LSC.1046
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert Boni collection of material about photography
circa 1840-1983
UCLA Library Special Collections
Boni, Albert
LSC.1046
7.0 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
Albert Boni (1892-1981) originated the idea of a very small format for abridged classics called "The Little Leather Library," which were sold through Woolworth's (1914). He sold the book shop in 1917 and joined Horace Liveright to form the Boni-Liveright Publishing Company, which introduced the "Modern Library of the World's Best Classics". In 1923, he and his brother founded a firm which introduced "Boni Paper Books" and sold them by mail-order subscription; the firm also published such controversial and influential writers as Marcel Proust, Colette, D.H. Lawrence, and Upton Sinclair. The collection consists of pamphlets, journal articles, bibliographies, catalogs, a scrapbook, notebooks, ephemera, photostats, photographs, and negatives relating to photography. Includes materials about technical processes and Boni's compilation, >A guide to the literature of photography and related subjects.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Albert Boni, 1965-1974.
Gift of William F. Boni, 1983.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303983606533
Biography
Boni was born in 1892 in New York City; attended Harvard University; in 1912, with his brother Charles, he established the Washington Square Book Shop, a gathering place for Bohemian intellectuals; about 1914 originated the idea of a very small format for abridged classics called "The Little Leather Library," which were sold through Woolworth's; sold the book shop in 1917 and joined Horace Liveright to form the Boni-Liveright Publishing Company, which introduced the "Modern Library of the World's Best Classics"; in 1923 he and his brother founded a firm which introduced "Boni Paper Books" and sold them by mail-order subscription; the firm also published such controversial and influential writers as Marcel Proust, Colette, D.H. Lawrence, and Upton Sinclair; the firm finally failed with the depression, and Boni later created the Readex Microprint Corporation; he died on July 13, 1981 in Ormond Beach, Florida.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of pamphlets, journal articles, bibliographies, catalogs, a scrapbook, notebooks, ephemera, photostats, photographs, and negatives relating to photography. Includes materials about technical processes and Boni's compilation, A guide to the literature of photography and related subjects. Also includes photographs relating to Louis Daguerre, Claude Niépce de Saint-Victor, and William Henry Fox Talbot.
Related Material
Albert and Charles Boni, Incorporated Records (Collection 1462). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Publishers and publishing -- United States -- Archives.; Photography -- Archives.; Boni, Albert, 1892-1981--Archives.
- Pamphlets re photography and the chemisty of photography., (5 folders). (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  English and foreign language publications.
- Pamphlets re photography and the chemistry of photography. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Pamphlets re color-photography. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Pamphlets re x-rays. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets re moving-pictures. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Pamphlets concerning microfilm and photostats. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous catalogs concerning photography and photographic equipment (Dealers'). (Box 2, Folder 6)
- >A guide to the literature of photography and related subjects. Compiled by Albert Boni. New York: Morgan & Lester, 1944.; 2 copies. (Supplement no.18 for Photo-Lab-Index) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Pyroxylin photographic and cinematograph films - patents. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Pyroxylin photographic and cinematograph films - bibliography. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Holograph letter to John A. Tennant. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  re an article for Photo-Miniature, Who Discovered Photography, together with photographs used to illustrate the article.
  Included are photographs relating to Daguerre, Niépce, and Fox-Talbot. Subject entries for these names are in the catalog.
- Photostats re a Mathew Brade carte-de-visite. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Photomechanical processes - bilbiolography of Library of Congress holdings. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous bibliographies concerning photography., (2 folders). (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Unidentified negatives. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous photographs. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- >The Atlantic., December 1957. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Articles re photography., Photocopies. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Journal articles re photography. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings re photography and photographers. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Magazine clippings - chiefly various examples of photography. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous ephemera. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- >Daedalus, journal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences., Winter 1960. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- >Aperture (vol.2 no.3-vol.12 no.4), 1953-1965.; 12 issues (2 folders). (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Bibliographies concerning photography. Foreign language publications. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Museum of Modern Art, New York. >A report on the Film Library, 1941-1956 (vol.24, no.1), Fall 1956. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Pamphlet on J.S. Mertle's photomechanic collection. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets on photographic exhibits. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Pamphlet on photographic spectrum of comet. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- List of books and articles by C.E.K. Mees. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous ephemera, camera catalogs, catalogs of photographers supplies and sundries. (Box 6)
  General note
  Gift of William Boni, 1983.
- Miscellaneous. (Box 7)
- Prints on photography. (Box 8)
- Microphotography. (Box 8)
- Literature of invention. (Box 8)
- Scrapbook with photos. (Box 8)
- Scrapbook - photographers., (2 scrapbooks). (Box 9)
- Subject indexes. (Box 9)
- Photographers / photographic history. (Box 9)
- Photomechanical process. (Box 10)
- Diazotype - Ozalid., 1927. (Box 10)
- Photography books sold. (Box 10)
- Photographers / History of photography. (Box 10)
- Aerial photography. (Box 10)
- Tennant notebook., (2 notebooks). (Box 10)
- "Persons." (Box 11)
- Physical development. (Box 11)
- "Collotype." (Box 11)
- Reprints, bibliographies. (Box 11)
- Beaumont Newhall checklist. (Box 11)
- Ephemera. (Box 11)
- Printed material - ephemera, catalogs, articles, technical pamphlets. (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)